chapter 67 cutting in it was a Saturday night and such a sabbath as followed
Exeicio professors of Sabbath breaking are all whalemen. The Ivory Peekquad was
turned into what seemed a shambble, every sailor a butcher. You would have
thought we were offering up 10,000 red oxen to the sea gods.
In the first place, the enormous cutting tackles, among other ponderous things,
comprising a cluster of blocks generally painted green, and which no single man
can possibly lift. This vast bunch of grapes was swayed up to the main top and
firmly lashed to the lower mast head, the strongest point anywhere above a
ship's deck. The end of the hawerlike rope winding through these intricacies
was then conducted to the windless, and the huge lower block of the tackles was
swung over the whale. To this block the great blubber hook, weighing some 100
lb, was attached, and now suspended in stages over the side. Starbucks and
Stub, the mates, armed with their long spades, began cutting a hole in the body
for the insertion of the hook just above the nearest of the two side fins. This
done, a broad semic-ircular line is cut round the hole, the hook is inserted,
and the main body of the crew striking up a wild chorus, now commence heaving
in one dense crowd at the windless, when instantly the entire ship careens over
on her side. Every bolt in her starts like the nail heads of an old house in
frosty weather. She trembles, quivers, and nods her frighted mast heads to the
sky. More and more she leans over to the whale, while every gasping heave of the
windless is answered by a helping heave from the billows, till at last a swift,
startling snap is heard. With a great swash, the ship rolls upward and
backwards from the whale, and the triumphant tackle rises into sight,
dragging after it, the disengaged semic-ircular end of the first strip of
blubber. Now, as the blubber envelops the whale precisely as the rind does an
orange, so it is stripped off from the body precisely as an orange is sometimes
stripped by spiralizing it. For the strain constantly kept up by the
windless continually keeps the whale rolling over and over in the water, and
as the blubber in one strip uniformly peels off along the line called the
scarf, simultaneously cut by the spades of Starbucks and Stub, the mates, and
just as fast as it is thus peeled off, and indeed by that very act itself, it
is all the time being hoisted higher and higher loft till its upper end grazes
the main top. The men at the windless then cease heaving, and for a moment or
two the prodigious blood dripping mass sways to and fro, as if let down from
the sky, and everyone present must take good heed to dodge it when it swings,
else it may box his ears and pitch him headlong overboard.
One of the attending harpooners now advances with a long, keen weapon called
a boarding sword, and watching his chance, he dexrously slices out a
considerable hole in the lower part of the swaying mass. into this hole. The
end of the second alternating great tackle is then hooked so as to retain a
hold upon the blubber in order to prepare for what follows, whereupon this
accomplished swordsman, warning all hands to stand off, once more makes a
scientific dash at the mass, and with a few sidelong, desperate lunging
slicings, severs it completely in twain, so that while the short lower part is
still fast, the long upper strip, called a blank, blanket piece swings clear and
is all ready for lowering. The heavers forward now resume their song, and while
the one tackle is peeling and hoisting a second strip from the whale, the other
is slowly slackened away, and down goes the first strip through the main
hatchway right beneath into an unfernished parlor called the blubber
room, into this twilight apartment.
Sunundry, nimble hands keep coiling away the long blanket piece as if it were a
great live mass of pleated serpents. And thus the work proceeds, the two tackles
hoisting and lowering simultaneously, both whale and windless heaving, the
heavers singing, the blubber room gentlemen coiling, the mates scarfing,
the ships straining, and all hands swearing occasionally by way of
assuaging the general friction.